Okay בוקר טוב Boker Tov today's דף Daf is דף כ"א. Daf
Chaf Aleph. גוט מועד Gut Moed I should also say and we
pick up at the very bottom of כ"א עמוד ב' Chaf Amud
Bet last two lines of כ"א עמוד ב' Chaf Amud Bet and
we enter into a new question so let's take a look over
there. So
the גמרא Gemara there
says אמר רב יצחק בר אדא לא הותרו פסי ביראות אלא לעולי
רגלים בלבד. Amar Rav Yitzchak Bar Adda Lo Hutru Passei Biraot Ella
LeOlei Regalim Bilvad. So now we're at the very beginning of the
second line two lines from the bottom. אמר רב יצחק בר אדא
Amar Rav Yitzchak Bar Adda לא הותרו פסי ביראות אלא לעולי רגלים
בלבד. Lo Hutru Passei Biraot Ella LeOlei Regalim Bilvad. They only allowed
the פסי ביראות Passei Biraot this whole special leniency which does not
even the majority of the areas not covered only for the people
that were coming up for the רגל Regel not for other person.
Now we'll discuss in a minute whether this means that that initially
have to have been the motivation or whether that means even in
an ongoing way the only people that can use it are the
people that are עולי לרגל. Olei LeRegel. So there you have anyway
very relevant to today during חול המועד. Chol HaMoed. Anyway
so that was a special allowance because there were so many people
coming up and all their animals and whatever we had to find
more way to create greater spaces that they could have their animals
drink over שבת. Shabbat. Not over יום טוב Yom Tov interestingly. It
was really just for the שבת. Shabbat. For יום טוב Yom Tov
you wouldn't be an issue.
והתניא VeHaTanya but did we teach in a ברייתא Baraita לא הותרו
פסי ביראות אלא לגבי בהמה בלבד. Lo Hutru Passei Biraot Ella Legabei
Behema Bilvad. It was only for the sake of animals not for
the sake of human drinking. So מאי בהמה Mai Behema says the
גמרא Gemara בהמת עולי רגלים. Behemet Olei Regalim. So now we have
combined the limits of both of these statements. Only for the animals
of the people that are עולי לרגל. Olei LeRegel. So if you're
doing it for a normal person or you're doing it for
somebody that is a normal animal it's not allowed. It's only for
the people that are עולי לרגל Olei LeRegel and even for them
not for them to drink but only for their animals to drink.
So now the גמרא Gemara says אבל אדם Aval Adam that why
shouldn't we be concerned about humans? I mean you know they need
to drink too. So the גמרא Gemara says
אבל אדם מטפס ועולה ומטפס ויורד. Aval Adam Mitapes VeOleh VeMitapes VeYored.
A person can sort of like you know lower himself down and
lower himself up. It's actually interesting it has the reverse order first
it says going up. But anyway a person can scale down and
scale up the wall. Now not always and that's pretty dangerous so
it's so crazy. So you mean you have this whole setup with
this פסי ביראות Passei Biraot and I can't do it and I
have to go scale down the wall. So let's read a little
bit more and then I'll tell you what תוספות Tosafot does to
moderate this גמרא Gemara a little bit. איני Eini says the גמרא
Gemara is this really true? והאמר רב יצחק והאמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל לא הותרו פסי ביראות אלא לבאר מים חיים בלבד. VeHa'amar Rav
Yitzchak VeHa'amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel Lo Hutru Passei Biraot Ella LeVe'er
Mayim Chayim Bilvad. So if they only allowed it for a live
spring of water so it has to be not just collected rainwater
but only something that's that's you know that's really coming from an
underground spring an underground well. ואי לבהמה Vee LeBehema and if it's
for an animal מאי לי חיים מאי לי מכונסים? Mai Li Chayim
Mai Li Mechunasim? Why do I care if it's from an underground
well and if it's live water? Why do I care if it's
gathered rainwater?
So now of course you could give an answer which the גמרא
Gemara said before about a concern about whether you know whether it
will dry up and then it dries up there's no more water
and there's no more of a of an allowance for the פסי
ביראות. Passei Biraot. Therefore you want it to be not just gathered
water but some coming from a live underground well. Nevertheless the גמרא
Gemara here understands that the emphasis is on the fact
that that type of water is potable whereas the rainwater not necessarily.
At least for humans. So why would it matter if the whole
focus is for animals? So the גמרא Gemara says בעינן מידי דחזי
לאדם. Be'inan Midi DeChazi Le'adam.
Yeah you need something that even though it's for the sake of
animals you want it to be fit for human consumption. Now why?
So if you take a look at רש"י Rashi רש"י Rashi says
מידי דחזי לאדם Midi DeChazi Le'adam two lines from the top כיון
דמים משוי לה מחיצה בעינן מים חשובים. Keivan DeMayim Mashvi Leh Mechitza
Be'inan Mayim Chashuvim. It makes it more important. Now even so though
if humans are not allowed to drink from it it becomes pretty
strange. So if you take a look at תוספות Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
makes a statement that makes this גמרא Gemara a little more understandable.
תוספות Tosafot says מידי דחזי לאדם בעינן Midi DeChazi Le'adam Be'inan ואופצי
דגמלא דלעיל. VeOfsei DeGamla DeLe'el.
First of all he says why you allowed to feed your animal
grain within this space? Remember you could feed your camel if it's
only for the water. היינו נמי במידי דחזי לאדם Hainu Nami BeMidi
DeChazi Le'adam and also תוספות Tosafot says the grain presumably is not
fit for human consumption. Okay maybe it is fit for human consumption.
אינמי Ina Nami
and then he goes on. Now four lines now the last of
the wide lines ואם תאמר Ve'im Tomar if you say אמאי בעינן
מידי דחזי לאדם כיון דלא שרי אלא לצורך בהמה? Amai Be'inan Midi
DeChazi Le'adam Keivan DeLo Shari Ella Letzorech Behema? Right don't just tell
me it makes it important why is that if it's only לצורך
בהמה? Letzorech Behema? So he says ויש לומר שאם דלה לצורך בהמה
ונשתייר שם שרי לאדם VeYesh Lomar She'im Dela Letzorech Behema VeNishtayer Sham
Shari Le'adam that
if you drew the water for for human consumption then it is
then it's. So that'll be to be permissible even for excuse me
if you drew the water for animal consumption then it's going to
be permissible even for even for human consumption. So that already makes
the position a lot less a lot more understandable a lot better.
And then תוספות Tosafos goes on to say let's see the next
line here in תוספות. Tosafos.
תוספות Tosafos says the following he says where were we?
הא דאמרינן לקמן Ha de'amrinan lekaman
and that we're about to say we haven't gotten to it yet
but let's just read it in a minute הא דאמרינן בסמוך Ha
de'amrinan besamuch ואם היו רחבים לאדם נמי שרי Ve'im hayu rechavim le'adam
nami shari היינו לדלות לכתחילה לצורך אדם. Hainu lidlot lechatchila letzorech adam.
Okay
so then תוספות Tosafos says then later we'll say a case where
actually it's not possible to scale down the wall and there he
says it's permissible even for and the גמרא Gemara there says not
possible to scale down the wall it's permissible even for humans. So
תוספות Tosafos just got through saying that it is permissible for humans
if you drew it for the sake of the בהמה behemah says
okay that case it would be permissible even לכתחילה lechatchila to draw
it for humans. And then תוספות Tosafos has an even more permissive
answer he says אי נמי הא דאמרינן לא הותרו אלא לצורך בהמה
היינו תחילת התיקון Inami ha de'amrinan lo hutru ella letzorech behemah hainu
techilas hatikkun
that's only when you set it up you have to have basically
do it in mind for the sake of the בהמה behemah אבל
בשכבר נתקן לצורך בהמה שרי אף לצורך אדם לכתחילה לדלות. aval beshekvar
nitkan letzorech behemah shari af letzorech adam lechatchila lidlot.
Okay so now תוספות Tosafos says is the following. This גמרא Gemara
makes it sound like you have this whole setup and you can
only use the water for feeding animals of all things. So תוספות
Tosafos says two leniencies. One leniency is feeding the animals for what
do you call it one leniency is that if you drew it
for animals you can use the leftover water. And the other leniency
is that even you can even draw it for humans once the
initial setup was for the sake of animals. So certainly making this
much more understandable that once you have the setup and the setup
was legitimate you can do it even for humans. Okay now we
continue and the גמרא Gemara says as follows
let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says גופא gufa
so let's go back to the original statement לא הותרו פסי ביראות
אלא לבהמה בלבד lo hutru pasei biros ella lebehemah bilvad it was
only allowed for animals אבל אדם מטפס ועולה מטפס ויורד aval adam
metapes ve'oleh metapes veyored but human let him scale down and up
the wall. But ואם היו רחבים ve'im hayu rechavim if it was
too wide you know it's only if it's narrow can you scale
down the wall אפילו אדם נמי afilu adam nami even for a
person and again what does it mean even for a person? So
תוספות Tosafos has two explanations.
It
either means it either means again that you can do it for
a person that
it either means you can do it for a person that excuse
me one second.
It either means that you can do it for a person that
you can that a person is allowed
that you don't לכתחילה lechatchila you can do it for a person
if it's too wide or you don't have to use leftover water.
But
again remember
hello alright but again remember that if you're doing it for that
if you're doing that according to תוספות Tosafos you can do it
if you made it originally for animals people could use it even
לכתחילה lechatchila so this allowance here that if it's too wide means
that if it's too wide you don't even have to לכתחילה lechatchila
make it for animals you can לכתחילה lechatchila make it for people
or you don't have to wait to use the leftover you can
לכתחילה lechatchila draw the water. But again remember according to תוספות Tosafos
that even in the other cases it's only really a problem if
it's if in terms of originally how you set it up but
once you've set it up for animals you can go ahead and
use it for people. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara continues one
two three we're about eight lines from the top by the asterisk.
ולא ימלא אדם מים ויתן לפני בהמתו Velo yemalei adam mayim veyiten
lifnei behemeto you cannot fill up water and this was the line
we had before in the גמרא Gemara if you're on yesterday that
don't hold the vessel directly in front of the animal אבל ממלא
הוא ושופך לפני בהמה ושותה מאליה aval memale hu veshofech lifnei behemah
veshota me'eleha you can pour it into the trough and the animal
can drink. So this sounded like you can't hold the vessel because
you'll go to follow after the animal and we had a whole
long discussion about that yesterday so we sort of quickly repeat it
now. מתקיף לה רבנן Matkif lah ravanan so רבנן ravanan asked אם
כן מה הועילו פסי ביראות im kein mah ho'ilu pasei biros what
good is the פסי ביראות pasei biros if you can't feed it
to your animal? גמרא Gemara says מה הועילו mah ho'ilu what do
you mean what good is it? למלאות lemalot to put it into
the trough so okay so you can't fill it and hold in
the vessel it's still good to put it in the trough. למלאות
מן? Lemalot man? אלא Ella no here's my question מה הועילו ראש
ורובו של פרה mah ho'ilu rosh verubo shel parah
why if you're not going to be holding the vessel why did
we limit it to the case of a majority of the cow?
Even if it's not the majority of the cow you're not holding
onto the vessel so what's the concern about what you're going to
do?
So even if the cow will go out as long as you've
poured the water in and you're not doing anything anymore what's the
concern? So אמר אביי amar abaye so here's where אביי abaye says
the statement that we used extensively yesterday הכא במאי עסקינן hacha bemai
askinan what are we talking about. באבוס העומד ברשות הרבים be'evus ha'omed
birshus harabbim גבוה עשרה ורוחב ארבע gavo'ah asarah verochav arba וראשו נכנס
לבין הפסים. verosho nichnas lebein hapasim.
So again, this whole story that what you're doing is you're actually
carrying it out to the cow
and over this trough that is itself רשות היחיד reshus hayachid and
the concern is you'll see something broken and you'll take the vessel
down and then take it back up and so on and so
forth. But yes, you are allowed to hold onto the vessel. And
this gets back to the whole discussion yesterday, whether the case in
the משנה mishna was whether you were holding on to the cow
and the vessel or not. Are you allowed to just hold onto
the vessel without holding onto the cow? And the גמרא gemara here
assumes, and this is what motivates אביי Abaye's statement, that if you
were not allowed to hold onto the vessel, then there would be
no point of limiting ourselves to ראשו ורובו rosho verubo of the
cow. So therefore because of that, it says that this case is
a special case. But normally you are allowed to hold onto the
vessel, and that's why we require ראשו ורובו rosho verubo of the
cow so you don't accidentally step out. Okay, so now we've said
two things. We've said that the whole purpose of this was for
עולי רגלים olei regalim and for their animals, animals of עולי רגלים
olei regalim actually, so the combination of the two, but then תוספות
Tosafos limits it to say once that was how it was made
then even humans can drink from it, or at least once you
drew it for animals they could use the leftover. And this whole
issue about not holding onto the vessel that אביי Abaye comes to
immediately moderate. Okay, now the גמרא gemara continues as follows.
Where are we?
אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב, Amar Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba
amar Rav, אין בורגנין בבבל, ein burganin be'Bavel, ופסי ביראות בחוצה לארץ.
ufasi birayos be'chutz la'aretz. There are no בורגנין burganin in בבל. Bavel.
בורגנין burganin are like little way stations that they had outside of
the city, little huts that they had for שומרים, shomrim, for people
that would watch the fields. And what those would do is those
would extend the תחום tchum of the city because as long as
you have everyone within seventy and two-thirds אמות, amos, then the city
is then it's considered to be an extension of the boundaries of
the city. So that does not apply in בבל, Bavel, which is
interesting. And you don't have פסי ביראות pasi birayos in חוצה לארץ.
chutz la'aretz. Now חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz is basically everything that's outside
of Israel that's not בבל. Bavel. Because בבל Bavel is not included
in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz is much more
the places that were what do you call it? That did not
have the same rabbinic centers as בבל. Bavel. בבל Bavel was literally
Babylonia, נהרדעא, Neharde'a, פומבדיתא Pumbedisa and so on. Okay, so these do
not apply, one of them in בבל Bavel and one of them
in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Let's see why not.
So the גמרא gemara says like this.
בורגנין בבבל לא. burganin be'Bavel lo. Why do you not have these
בורגנין, burganin, these huts, these way stations in בבל? Bavel? Meaning even
if you did it wouldn't count to extend the walls of the
city. So דשכיחי בדקי, deshchichi bidkei, because there are lots
of like rain
and therefore that's going to wash them away. And therefore even if
they're there, they're not considered to be legitimate, I mean they're not
considered to extend the water of the city, the boundaries of the
city.
So there's a lot of
flooding actually, better translation. Okay, so that's why they don't work in
בבל. Bavel. And ופסי ביראות בחוצה לארץ, ufasi birayos be'chutz la'aretz, and
פסי ביראות pasi birayos don't work in חוצה לארץ, chutz la'aretz, why
not? לא דלא שכיחי מתיבתא, lo delo shchichi mesivsa, because they do
not have ישיבות. yeshivos. Now of course this immediately assumes, you would
say, well if we just said it's for עולי רגלים, olei regalim,
obviously it can't apply anywhere outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael or
can't apply anywhere after חורבן הבית. churban habayis. So the גמרא gemara
immediately assumes that no, that we would take that idea of עולי
רגלים olei regalim and we would extend it to similar circumstances when
there's like a lot of tourism or a lot of outsiders coming
into the city. So therefore it assumes that it would have applied
in בבל Bavel because of all the people that are traveling there
for the sake of ישיבות. yeshivos. But it does not apply in
חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz because they don't have ישיבות, yeshivos, so you
don't have the חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz. I should point out that
very subtly, just really in its assumption, the גמרא gemara has said
a profound thing. That basically it said that now there's a חורבן
הבית, churban habayis, what substitutes עולי רגלים olei regalim and what substitutes
the center of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash in ארץ ישראל? Eretz
Yisrael? It's the ישיבות yeshivos in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz and people
coming to learn in the ישיבות yeshivos in חוצה לארץ. chutz la'aretz.
So it's really that whole sort of replacement of a rabbinic Torah
centered Judaism from a temple centered Judaism. Okay, so that's why but
it does not apply in חוצה לארץ chutz la'aretz and only applies
in בבל. Bavel.
So that's his statement.
Then the גמרא gemara then says איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say
אמר רב ירמיה בר אבא אמר רב, Amar Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba
amar Rav, אין בורגנין ופסי ביראות לא בבבל ולא בחוצה לארץ. ein
burganin ufasi birayos lo be'Bavel velo be'chutz la'aretz. Neither of them apply
in either places. בורגנין בבבל לא דשכיחי בדקי, burganin be'Bavel lo deshchichi
bidkei,
these huts don't apply in בבל Bavel because of the flooding. בחוצה
לארץ נמי לא דשכיחי גנבי, be'chutz la'aretz nami lo deshchichi ganvei, and
outside of בבל Bavel because of theft. So if you leave a
hut standing there, people are going to come and steal the hut.
So therefore it doesn't apply in either places even if you make
them, they're not considered serious domiciles. פסי ביראות בבבל לא, pasi birayos
be'Bavel lo, now why doesn't פסי ביראות pasi birayos apply in בבל?
Bavel? Whatever happened to what we talked about about the people traveling
for the ישיבות? yeshivos? דשכיחי מיא, deshchichi maya,
again because there's so much water and flooding, so therefore there's no
need, not like there's no legitimacy. There's no need to allow the
special institution which allows people access to the wells. There's so much
water around all the time.
And בחוצה לארץ נמי לא *bechutza l'aretz nami lo* דלא שכיחי מסיבתא
*delo shechichi masivata* and in חוצה לארץ *chutz l'aretz* not because there's
not that type of travel and therefore there's not a legitimate need
either. Okay. So that was a couple statements in the name of
a רב Rav, ירמיה בר אבא *Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba*. Okay, so
now we go on. So אמר ליה Amar lei, רב חסדא Rav
Chisda למרי בריה דרב הונא בריה דרב ירמיה בר אבא *amar lei
Rav Chisda le-Mari brei de-Rav Huna brei de-Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba*. So
since we quoted רב Rav ירמיה בר אבא *Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba*,
here we have another statement that רב Rav חסדא *Rav Chisda* said
to מרי *Mari* the son of רב Rav, הונא *Rav Huna*, the
son of רב ירמיה בר אבא *Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba*. אמרי *amri*
עשיתו מברנש לבי כנישתא דדניאל *asitu mi-Barnash le-vei knishta de-Daniel*. They said
that you came from ברנש *Barnash* which is one place in בבל
*Bavel* to the בית ככנסת *beis knesses* of דניאל *Daniel*. The תורה
Torah. *Torah* speaks about, whatever the תנ"ך *Tanach*, the ספר דניאל *Sefer
Daniel* speaks about it when דניאל *Daniel* was in גלות *Galus* he
would pray three times a day. So there was a certain place
that they identified as the בית כנסת Knesset *beis knesses* of דניאל
*Daniel*. So I heard that on שבת *Shabbos* you traveled from ברנש
*Barnash* to the בית כנסת *beis knesses* of דניאל *Daniel*. דהוי תלתא
פרסי בשבתא *dahavi tlasa parsei be-Shabbasta*. That was three פרסאות *parsaos* on
שבת *Shabbos*. Now a פרסה *parsa* is four מיל *mil*, you're allowed
to travel on שבת *Shabbos* a מיל *mil*, 2,000 אמות *amos* outside
of city limits. So this is three פרסאות *parsaos*, that's 12 times
2,000 אמות *amos*, 12 times the usual שבת תחום *Shabbos techum*. How
did you do this? אמאי
*amai*
סמכיתו אבורגנין *samchitu a-burganin*? Why did you rely on these huts? Presumably
that's what you relied on, it must have been a lot of
huts. האמר אבוה דאבוך משמיה דרב *ha-amar avuha de-avuch mishmeih de-Rav*, your
father's father, this was right, remember he was the grandson of רב
ירמיה בר אבא *Rav Yirmiyah bar Abba*. So it was your father's
father who said in the name of רב *Rav*, אין בורגנין בבבל
*ein burganin be-Vavel*, we don't rely on these huts in בבל *Bavel*.
So נפק *nafak*, he went outside, ואחוי ליה הנך מטוותא *ve-achvei lei
hanach masvata*. He pointed to him the various cities. רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says מטוותא *masvata* means like you could either mean like little villages,
תוספות Tosafot, *Tosafos*, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means like destroyed cities
דהוו דמיבלעי בשבעים אמה ושיריים *de-havu de-mivlei be-shivim ama ve-shirayim* that each
one was within 70 and two-thirds אמות *amos*, which is not much
at all. 70 and two-thirds אמות *amos* is what? It's like about
100 feet, 150 feet maybe. So there must have been an enormous
amount of them. Anyway, and they were all, each one of these
were like lined up from where he came from ברנש *Barnash* all
the way to the בית כנסת *beis knesses* of דניאל *Daniel*. So
it's a little hard to imagine, I mean my God, if it
was three פרסאות *parsaos* that was
12,000, that was let's see, a פרסה *parsa* is 8,000 אמות *amos*,
so that was 24,000 אמות *amos*. That's a lot, that is a
lot. So how he managed to do all of that with little
things that were spaced 70 and some שיריים *shirayim*, but maybe it
went 70 and שיריים *shirayim* to get to the next city, and
then you had the whole length of the next city, and then
it used these things as connectors to the next city. It's hard
to imagine you had all of these lined up for three פרסאות
*parsaos*. But again, as long as you get these lined up to
get you to a city, then you have the entire length of
a city and then they can connect you to the next one.
Now interesting little side point about תוספות *Tosafos* about מטוותא *masvata*. If
you look at תוספות *Tosafos*, he says משמע דכפרים קטנים אחווי ליה
הנך מטוותא משמע דכפרים קטנים מיקרו מטוותא *mashma de-kfarim ktanim achvei lei
hanach masvata mashma de-kfarim ktanim mikru masvata* that תוספות *Tosafos* initially thinks
not like רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. It's not a destroyed city, but it's
a little village, and that these are called מטוותא *masvata*. פרק קמא
דגיטין קרי לערים גדולות מטוותא *Perek kama de-Gittin kari le-arim gdolos masvata*.
But in the first פרק *perek* in גיטין *Gittin* only big cities
are called מטוותא *masvata*. מטוותא *Masvata* by the way is a plural
of מטא *masa*, city. דקאמר מטוותא דארעא דישראל כחשיב גבי קינא דדימינא
ודדא *de-ka'amar masvata de-ar'a de-Yisrael ke-chashiv gavi kina de-dimina ve-deda*. ומתוך כך
*u-mitechach* anyway, נראה *nireh*, here's the key line, דאין להקפיד ממה שכתוב
בבגט מטא פלוני בין עיר גדולה בין עיר קטנה *de-ein le-hakpid mi-mah
she-kasuv be-get masa ploni bein ir gdola bein ir ktana*. Right, what
we do in a גט *get* is when we identify the city,
we call it מטא פלוני *masa ploni*, the following city. And תוספות
*Tosafos* thinks if מטא *masa* only means a city, not a town,
then how do we write the word מטא *masa* by a town?
So he wants to prove from this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that the
word מטא *masa* even means a town, not just a city. But
he says but then he admits that רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it
does mean a city just a destroyed city. So therefore that would
not be a good evidence to that. Also interesting that a destroyed
city is good enough for connecting the space for עירובין eiruvin *eiruvin*
purposes. Okay. So it is possible if you have enough connectors, it
is possible to travel quite a long distance on שבת *Shabbos* and
that's עירוב Eruv תחומין T'chumim *eiruv techumin* is something we will see
in a little bit. Okay. Now אמר רב חסדא *amar Rav Chisda*.
Now we're going to go on a little דרש *drash* digression and
we'll see how it circles back to our discussions. אמר רב חסדא
*Amar Rav Chisda* דרש מרי בר מר Mari bar Mar *darash Mari
bar Mar*. So מרי בר מר *Mari bar Mar* expounded the following
way. מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv, *Mai de-chsiv*, what's meant by the פסוק
pasuk, *pasuk* לכל תכלה ראיתי קץ רחבה מצותך מאד rachava mitzvatecha me'od.
*le-chol tichla ra'isi ketz rechava mitzvascha me'od*, for all ends I have
seen an end, but your מצוות mitzvot *mitzvos* are very wide. Everything
else in the world I know where it ends, your מצוות mitzvot,
*mitzvos* I see no end to them. דבר זה אמר דוד dud
ולא פירשו *davar zeh amar David ve-lo pirsho*. דוד *David* said it
and didn't explain it. What does it mean? What is the actual,
you know, limit of the מצוות mitzvot *mitzvos* and of the תורה
שבעל פה Torah shebe'al peh *Torah she-be'al peh* we're see we're talking
about? אמרו איוב ולא פירשו *amru Iyov ve-lo pirsho*. איוב *Iyov* said
it and didn't explain it. אמר יחזקאל ולא פירשו *amar Yechezkel ve-lo
pirsho*. יחזקאל *Yechezkel* said it and didn't explain it. עד שבא זכריה
בן עדו ופירשו *ad she-ba Zecharia ben Ido u-pirsho*. And till זכריה
*Zecharia* came and explained it. אמר דוד ולא פירשו *Amar David velo
peirsho*. דוד *David* said it and didn't explain it דכתיב *dechtiv* לכל
תכלה ראיתי קץ רחבה מצותך מאד me'od, *L'chol tichla ra'iti ketz, rechava
mitzvatcha me'od*. They're very wide, didn't say how wide. אמר איוב ולא
פירשו *Amar Iyov velo peirsho*. איוב *Iyov* said it and didn't explain
it דכתיב *dechtiv* the verse says by איוב *Iyov* ארוכה מארץ מדה
ורחבה מני ים *Arucha me'eretz midah, urchava mini yam* that its length
is greater than then then the land and it's wider than the
sea. אמר יחזקאל ולא פירשו *Amar Yechezkel velo peirsho*. יחזקאל *Yechezkel* said
it and didn't explain it דכתיב *dechtiv* ויפרוש אותה לפני *vayifros osa
lifanay* excuse me ויפרוש אותה לפני *vayifros osa lifanay* והיא כתובה פנים
ואחור panim ve-achor *v'hee chsuva panim v'achor*. He spread it out in
front of me and it was written front and back וכתוב עליה
קינים והגה והי *V'chasuv aleha kinim vahege vahi*. And it was written
on it קינים *kinim* and והגה *hege* and והי *hi*. What are
קינים *kinim* and והגה *hege* and והי *hi*? קינים זו פורעניותם של
צדיקים בעולם הזה *Kinim zo pur'aniyosam shel tzaddikim ba'olam hazeh*. קינים *Kinim*
are like the lamentations, its sufferings that צדיקים *tzaddikim* have to go
through in this world because they're rewarded in the world to come.
וכן הוא אומר קינה היא וקוננוה *V'chen hu omer kina hi v'konnuha*.
והגה *Vahege* so it speaks about lamentations. והגה זו מתן שכרן של
צדיקים לעתיד לבוא le'atid lavo *Hege zo matan secharan shel tzaddikim l'asid
lavo*. והגה *Hege* is, you know you could also say it means
woe, but here it's being translated as something positive or rejoicing. This
is the reward of the צדיקים *tzaddikim* in the future. וכן הוא
אומר עלי הגיון בכינור *V'chen hu omer alei higayon b'chinnor*. So a
sound of rejoicing on the כינור *kinnor* on the lute. והי זו
היא פורעניותם של רשעים resha'im לעתיד לבוא *Vahi zuhee pur'aniyosam shel resha'im
l'asid lavo*. והי *Hi* is woe and that's again the suffering of
wicked of the wicked people לעתיד לבוא *l'asid lavo* in the future.
וכן הוא אומר הוה על הוה תבוא עד תבוא *V'chen hu omer
hova al hova tavo ad tavo*. Okay, so anyway so all this
stuff is written. Now it's interesting we're talking about the מצוות mitzvot.
*mitzvot* but what's the connection to reward and punishment? But presumably it
means since the מצוות mitzvos *mitzvot* are so broad and so wide
and so on, that will lead to great reward for the צדיקים
*tzaddikim* and great suffering for the רשעים resha'im *resha'im*. Why it means
suffering for the צדיקים *tzaddikim* in this world not exactly clear. Anyway
everybody is describing how broad it is. עד שבא זכריה בן עדוא
*Ad sheba Zecharya ben Ido* until זכריה *Zecharya* came ופירשו *upeirsho* and
he explained it דכתיב *dechtiv* ויאמר אלי מה אתה רואה ואומר אני
רואה מגילה Megillah, עפה ארכה עשרים באמה *Vayomer elai mah atta ro'eh?
Va'omar ani ro'eh megilla afa, aruka esrim b'amma*. I see a, you
know, a spread out מגילה Megillah *megilla*. Its length is twenty אמות
*amot*. Now רש"י Rashi *Rashi* points out we're talking about divine אמות
*amot*, however long those are. ורחבה עשר באמה *V'rachba eser b'amma* and
it's ten אמות *amot* wide. וכי פשטת לה *V'chi pashat'la* so now
the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says so if it's folded over, if you
unfold it הוי לה עשרים בעשרים *havi lah esrim b'esrim*. So if
it's twenty by ten and it's folded, if you unfold it it's
twenty by twenty. וכתיב והיא כתובה פנים ואחור *U'chtiv v'hee chsuva panim
v'achor* and it's written front and back. וכי קלפת לה *V'chi kalaft'la*
so if you were to like split it, you know, if you
were to lay out the front and back side by side כמה
הוי לה ארבעים בעשרים *kama havi lah arba'im b'esrim*. Forty divine אמות
*amot* by twenty אמות *amot*. וכתיב *U'chtiv* and it says me now
how is that big as that relative to how big the world
is? Because we're using divine measurements. So it says מי מדד בשעלו
מים ושמים בזרת תיכן *Mi madad b'sha'alo mayim v'shamayim b'zeres tiken*. Who
measures in his like, you know, in his in his cloak whatever
the the hem, water and the heavens establishes with the זרת *zeret*.
זרת *Zeret* is the the size from your pinky to your finger
which is half of an אמה *amma*. So the heavens were made
with half of a divine אמה *amma* and these are forty by,
what did we say this was, twenty by twenty divine אמות *amot*.
נמצא כל עולם כולו אחד משלושים אלפים ומאתים בתורה *Nimtza kol olam
kulo echad mishloshim alafim u'masayim baTorah*. So assuming that the זרת *zeret*
is a half of an אמה *amma* in both directions so it
is a quarter of a square אמה *amma*. And the other thing
was twenty by twenty which is four hundred square אמות *amot*. So
what is the what is the proportion, the ratio of a quarter
to four hundred? So multiply by four, it is sixteen hundred. So
the whole world is, oops, that didn't work. Hold on. Let
me
see.
We said this was twenty by twenty is four hundred. This is
a quarter,
half and a half is a quarter.
This gets thirty two hundred.
What am I doing wrong?
Oh no, 'cause I didn't do the last part of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. I'm sorry, I didn't do the last part of the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Right, it was twenty by twenty and then you
laid the front and back side by side so it was forty
by twenty. Okay, so it's eight hundred. So it's eight hundred square
אמות *amot* and this is a quarter square אמה *amma* so eight
hundred by four is thirty two hundred. So the the size of
the תורה Torah *Torah* which here means presumably תורה שבעל פה Torah
shebe'al peh, *Torah shebe'al peh* is thirty two hundred times the size
of the world. נמצא כל עולם כולו אחד משלושת אלפים ומאתים בתורה
*Nimtza kol olam kulo echad mishloshet alafim u'matayim baTorah*. The entire world
is only one thirty two hundredth of the size of the תורה
Torah, *Torah*. Okay, so very interesting. What is that going to do
for us? So let's keep on looking. ואמר רב חסדא *V'amar Rav
Chisda* says רב חסדא *Rav Chisda* how is this relevant to our
larger discussion? דרש מרי בר מר *Darsh Mari bar Mar* so the
same מרי בר מר *Mari bar Mar* explicated מאי דכתיב mai dechtiv,
*mai dechtiv* what's meant by the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* והנה שני דודאי
תאנים מועדים לפני היכל ה' *V'hinei shenei dudaei te'enim mu'adim lifnei heichal
Hashem*. Two pots of figs set in front of the sanctuary of
God. הדודאי *Hadudai*. הדוד אחד תאנים טובות, one was good figs, מאד,
me'od, very good,
כתאני הבכורות, kite'enei habechorot, top of דף ע"ב, Daf ayin bet, like
the figs of the firstborn fruit, of the first
fruit. והדוד אחד, Vehadud echad, and the other one, תאנים רעות, te'enim
ra'ot, were very bad, מאד, very bad figs, אשר לא תאכלנה מרע,
asher lo te'achalnuh meira, that could not be eaten because they were
so disgusting. So, תאנים הטובות אלו צדיקים גמורים. te'enim hatovot elu tzaddikim
gemurim. Now the גמרא Gemara explicates, the good ones are the holy
righteous people. תאנים הרעות אלו רשעים גמורים, te'enim hara'ot elu resha'im gemurim,
the bad ones are the fully wicked people. ושמא תאמר, Veshema tomar,
lest you say, אבד סברם ובטל סיכוים, avad sivram uvatal sikuyam, that
their hope
and future has been negated, lost, like the רשעים have no hope
to them, they're a lost cause. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, הדודאים נתנו
ריח. haduda'im natnu rei'ach. So the דודאים, duda'im, this is quoting from
שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim, a little play on words דוד and דודאים.
duda'im. דודאים duda'im are these mandrakes. But anyway, so they've given off
a smell. אלו ואלו עתידים שיתנו ריח, Elu ve'elu atidim sheyitnu rei'ach,
in the future they will all give off a smell, even the
רשעים have many מצוות mitzvos, and therefore, even they, even the ones
that are very wicked and disgusting, even they ultimately will give off
a beautiful smell and their goodness will be revealed לעתיד לבוא in
the future. Okay. דרש רבא, Darash Rava, now that we're דורש'ינג darshening
פסוקים pesukim from שיר השירים, Shir Hashirim, we're going to do that
for a little while before we get back to the main theme
here, which was the דרשות drashot by מרי בר מר and we'll
see how they connect to our larger theme. So, דרש רבא, Darash
Rava, Rava explicated, מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv what's meant by the פסוק,
pasuk הדודאים נתנו ריח? haduda'im natnu rei'ach? אלו בחורי ישראל שלא טעמו
טעם חטא. Elu bachurei Yisrael shelo ta'amu ta'am chet. These are, as
opposed to that it's all of them, both דוד'ס, dud's, דודאים duda'im
read as דודים dodim like the plural, both pots, no. These are
only the youth of Israel of the Jewish people that have never
yet sinned. So, and that's דודאים duda'im like this type
of mandrakes, these fresh sprouts that have not yet
grown and that have not yet sinned. I think the מהרש"א Maharsha
also says because these plants don't have much of a taste, so
that's לא טעמו טעם חטא. lo ta'amu ta'am chet. And now continuing
to do the דרשה: drasha: ועל פתחינו כל מגדים, Ve'al petacheinu kol
megadim, by our doorway is all types of delicacies. אלו בנות
ישראל, Elu benot Yisrael, שמגידות פתחיהן לבעליהן, shemagidot picheihen leva'aleihen, these are
the Jewish women that tell their husbands when they're a נדה niddah
and that they are so observant,
you know, it's all based on their reporting and they
always report faithfully to their husbands. לשון אחר, Lashon acher, another version:
שאוגדות פתחיהן לבעליהן, she'ogdot picheihen leva'aleihen, that they bind up their openings
to their husbands,
that they observe the laws and they don't have sex when they
are
נדות. niddot. חדשים גם ישנים, Chadashim gam yeshanim, new ones and old
ones. דודי צפנתי לך, Dodi tzafanti lach, my beloved I have longed
for you. אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amra Knesset Yisrael
lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so now the Jewish people say to God:
רבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel Olam, Master of the Universe, הרבה גזירות
גזרתי על עצמי יותר ממה שגזרת עלי. Harbeh gezeirot gazarti al atzmi
yoter mima shegazarta alai. So this will resonate with a lot of
people: I have made many prohibitions on myself much more than You
have prohibited on me. So now that we're in the middle of
פסח Pesach with like קטניות kitniyot and יום טוב שני, Yom Tov
Sheni, I think people can identify with this. So it's not just
what You've given to me. And the מהרש"א Maharsha ties it in
very much to the discussion a minute ago about נדה, niddah, the
whole idea of חומרא דרבי זירא Chumra deRabbi Zeira and a lot
of other חומרות chumrot of נדה. niddah. God, look how much I
love Your מצוות, mitzvot that not only is it what You tell
me, I go ahead and I add to them myself. וקיימתים, Vekiyamtim,
and I fulfilled all of them, both what You said and the
ones that I have added. חדשים גם ישנים. Chadashim gam yeshanim.
Okay, so
and that's all ודודי צפנתי לך vedodi tzafanti lach because how much
I have longed for you or maybe it's like I have treasured
for you, I have gathered them up as a storehouse. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, so רב חסדא לההוא מרבנן, lehahu meirabbanan, and Rav Chisda
said to one of the rabbinic students, דהוה מסדר אגדתא קמיה, dehava
mesader agadata kammeih, that was organizing the אגדתא agadata in front of
him, laying out the אגדתא, agadata, telling different אגדות. agadot. מי שמיע
לך חדשים גם ישנים מהו? Mi shemi'a lach chadashim gam yeshanim mahu?
Have you heard a nice דרשה drasha on חדשים גם ישנים? chadashim
gam yeshanim? אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said to him, אלו מצוות
קלות ואלו מצוות חמורות. Elu mitzvot kalot ve'elu mitzvot chamurot. Yeah, the
light מצוות mitzvot and the heavy מצוות. mitzvot. אמר ליה, וכי תורה
פעמיים פעמיים ניתנה? vechi Torah pa'amayim pa'amayim nitnah? What does it have
to do with old and new? The Torah wasn't given two times
and like the earlier one given first and the harsher, more stringent
ones given later. What does it have to do with old and
new? אלא הללו מדברי תורה והללו מדברי סופרים. Ella hallalu midivrei Torah
vehallalu midivrei soferim. Same point as before: the ones that were given
by God, by the Torah, those are the ישנים, yeshanim, and also
the חדשים, chadashim, those that are given by the sages, those get
added to it as well. Now we understand why רחבה מצותך מאד.
the מהרש"א Maharsha says that the reason קלות וחמורות kalot vechamurot had
that tie into חדשים גם ישנים chadashim gam yeshanim is you assumed
that the קלות kalot was because they were rabbinic, they were קל,
kal, they were more lenient than the ones that were biblical and
therefore those were the ones that were the חדשים, chadashim, so there
was maybe a miscommunication there. דרש רבא, Darsh Rava, so רבא Rava
explicated: מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv what's meant by the verse
ויותר מהמה בני הזהר עשות ספרים הרבה, veyoter mehema beni hizaher asot
sefarim harbe, and more than this my son you should be careful
the making of many books. What does that mean? בני הזהר בדברי
סופרים יותר מדברי תורה. beni hizaher bedivrei Sofrim yoter midivrei Torah. Be
careful of the rabbinic laws more than the Torah laws. Obviously that's
a little bit of an exaggeration, שדברי תורה יש בהן עשה ולא
תעשה, shedivrei Torah yesh bahen aseh velo ta'aseh, because biblical laws is
positive מצוות mitzvot. and negative מצוות, mitzvot ודברי סופרים, vedivrei Sofrim, but
when it comes to rabbinic laws, כל העובר על דברי סופרים חייב
מיתה, kol ha'over al divrei Sofrim chayav misa, anybody who transgresses the
words of the sages is deserving of death. And רש"י Rashi quotes
the famous פסוק pasuk that's quoted in other cases,
which is ופורץ גדר ישכנו נחש, uporetz geder yishchenu nachash, that one
that breaks through a גדר geder very much framing the rabbinic laws
as a גדר, geder, a fence, a protection for biblical laws, then
will be bit by a snake. So somehow you'll suffer great tragedy,
you'll suffer death. And there are times where the גמרא, Gemara we'll
actually see a case right here where the גמרא Gemara goes to
extremes about not wanting to go against rabbinic laws because of the
sense of not being a פורץ גדר, poretz geder, not going against
the norms that are set. So one could say that this is
just
a exaggeration for the sake of making people careful about it because
normally in all other halachic ways we don't treat rabbinic laws as
more strict than biblical laws, quite the opposite, but it's a certain
type of a rhetoric in order to get people to be very
careful about these. The מהרש"א Maharsha wants to say that maybe what
we mean is rabbinic laws that are coming to protect biblical laws
that are חייב מיתה. chayav misa. That he also finds it hard
to imagine that it's saying that a rabbinic law that's coming to
protect a simple negative transgression, like waiting between meat and milk or
something, that that would be worse than actually eating milk or meat
cooked together. So he says that most of what we're talking about
is those that are coming to protect against biblical laws that are
חייב מיתה. chayav misa. One way or the other, it certainly cannot
be understood fully in its simple sense. This also by the way
explains why it said before חדשים גם ישנים chadashim gam yeshanim ties
into that previous דרשה. drasha. Why are the חדשים, chadashim, the rabbinic
laws, mentioned first? Because here we're saying that you have to be
super careful with them.
Okay, and that's עשות ספרים הרבה. asot sefarim harbe. By the way,
I should point out, ויותר מהמה בני הזהר עשות ספרים הרבה veyoter
mehema beni hizaher asot sefarim harbe that the דברי סופרים divrei Sofrim
are much greater, they're very many, and you have to be very
careful. Okay. שמא
תאמר אם יש בהן ממש בפני מה לא נכתבו, shema tomar im
yesh bahen mamash bifnei ma lo nechtavu, and now lest you say
that if they're really so important why didn't God think about writing
them down? Why did it need for the sages to put them
down? So if they're really supposed to do them, why was it
only for the rabbis who made them up? אמר קרא עשות ספרים
הרבה אין קץ. amar kra asot sefarim harbe ein ketz. So because
it would have been the writing of many books without limit. So
here interpreting עשות ספרים asot sefarim a sort of a separate point
and connected directly the same point as before. Basically yeah, because it
would have been without any end. So therefore you had to give
it to a written תורה. Torah. It's a תורה שבעל פה Torah
she-be'al peh that we've been saying has no ends, but the תורה
שבכתב Torah shebichtav it has to be finite and manageable. Now part
of what this
also could reflect, and this is sort of indicated in the מהרש"א
Maharsha somewhat, is
that the rabbinic needs are more responding to sort of realities of
the time and
therefore it's not as sort of finite and it's more changes over
time and each one responds to a different time and its own
particular needs. But of course if that's true,
it's not like you get rid of the earlier stuff, which is
why you have the עשות ספרים אין קץ asot sefarim ein ketz
that it keeps on building and building and building but nevertheless there's
a responsiveness to the particular needs of the time. The גמרא Gemara
you don't see that, the גמרא Gemara just sort of seems to
say that this is tying into the previous theme that that would
just become too large to be manageable for תורה שבכתב. Torah shebichtav.
Somehow it is manageable as a תורה שבעל פה, Torah she-be'al peh
but it wouldn't have been manageable as a תורה שבכתב. Torah shebichtav.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues
ולהג הרבה יגיעת בשר, velahag harbe yegi'at basar, and great sort of
weariness of the flesh, what does this mean? So this is also
from קהלת. Kohelet. אמר רב פפא בריה דרב אחא בר
אדא משמיה דרב אחא בר עולא, amar Rav Papa brei deRav Acha
bar Adda mishmei deRav Acha bar Ulla, מלמד melamed this teaches you
שכל המלעיג על דברי חכמים, shekol hamal'ig al divrei chachamim, so tying
it into the previous theme about הזהר בדברי סופרים hizaher bedivrei Sofrim
and that they're just so many, and anybody who mocks the words
of the sages, so להג lahag is מלעיג mal'ig is to mock,
על דברי חכמים נידון בצואה רותחת, al divrei chachamim nidon betzoa rotachat,
will be judged with
boiling
excrement. So that's יגיעת בשר yegi'at basar the weariness of the flesh
is what the flesh sort of excretes.
if
you actually give thought to them and you delve into them טעם
בשר, ta'am basar, so יגיעת בשר yegi'at basar and you have יגיעה,
yegi'ah, you have effort, then it's בשר, basar, you taste flesh. And
again you you might sort of see it at the surface it
doesn't make any sense, it seems foolish. No, if you study them
it'll be
real, it'll be געשמאק, geshmak, it'll be like tasting meat. Okay, so
the whole point here is that the תורה שבעל פה Torah shebeal
peh, is enormously broad.
It is connected obviously to the fact that God has given it,
which is what we have in the earlier פסוקים, psukim, right? It's
פנים ואחור and all of that, it was given by God, רחבה
מני ים. rachava mini yam. I should also mention the מהרש''א Maharsha
has a nice explanation about what it means to be folded over
and front and back, and he says it refers to like פשט
רמז דרש סוד, Pshat Remez Drash Sod, that there's the stuff that's
hidden that's folded and then you have to expose it and uncover
it. And then and then you have this idea about how פרוש
parush we are about keeping them, not only the biblical laws, not
only the rabbinic laws, the חומרות chumrot that we add upon ourselves
and how careful we have to be about them and how how
terrible it would be to transgress. And the fact that they are
the תורה שבעל פה Torah sheba'al peh. is much wider and broader
than the תורה שבכתב, Torah she-bi-ktav, and somehow that's the explanation why
it wasn't given all straight from God. Okay, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan,
now we have a story that supports this idea about how serious
it is to keep rabbinic laws.
מעשה ברבי עקיבא שהיה חבוש בבית האסורין. ma'aseh be-Rabbi Akiva she-haya chavush
be-veit ha-asurin. This is a famous story. Rabbi Akiva was in jail,
was being locked up in jail by the Roman government. ורבי יהושע
הגרסי, ve-Rabbi Yehoshua Ha-Garsi, Rabbi Yehoshua Ha-Garsi, רש''י says it either is
just the name of his place or רש''י says it could also
mean that he would like from the word גריסין, grisin, he would
grind like
what do you call it bran. So Rabbi Yehoshua Ha-Garsi
was his attendant.
Where are we? ורבי יהושע הגרסי משרתו ve-Rabbi Yehoshua Ha-Garsi mesharto was
his attendant. בכל יום ויום היו מכניסין לו מים במידה. be-chol yom
va-yom hayu machnisin lo mayim be-midah. Every day they would bring in
to him water in a particular defined measure, a very specific amount
of water they were allowed to bring to him, not more. יום
אחד מצאו שומר בית האסורין. yom echad matzo shomer beit ha-asurin. One
day the jailer found him. אמר לו, amar lo, this Rabbi Yehoshua
Ha-Garsi, אתון היום מימך מרובים, atun hayom meimecha merubim, you have too
much water today. Now it could be that he was just making
all this up anyway. שמא לחפור בית האסורין אתה צריך, shema lachpor
beit ha-asurin atah tzarich, maybe are you using them to like get
the ground soft and you want to dig a tunnel and escape?
שפך
חציין ונתן לו חציין. shafach chetzyan ve-natan lo chetzyan. He poured half
off and gave him half. So he didn't have he had much
less than the normal amount of water he would bring. כשבא אצל
רבי עקיבא אמר לו, kesheba etzel Rabbi Akiva amar lo, when he
came to Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Akiva said to him: יהושע אי אתה
יודע שזקן אני וחיי תלויים בחייך, Yehoshua i atah yode'a she-zaken ani
ve-chayai tluyim be-chayecha, Yehoshua don't you know that I am that I
am old and my life depends on you on
what on your bringing me water every day? It's funny that he
says he's old, he's also in jail. Anyway, סח לו כל אותה
המאורע, sach lo kol otah ha-me'ora, he told him the whole story
about the jailer. אמר לו: amar lo: תן לי מים שאטול ידי.
ten li mayim she-etol yadai. He said to him, so fine, give
me the water so I can wash my hands and eat the
bread. אמר לו: amar lo: לשתות אין מגיעים ליטול ידיך מגיעים. lishtot
ein megi'im litol yadecha megi'im. There's not enough water here for you
to
drink, to wash your hands there's enough? Presumably the normal amount he
would bring him every day would be enough to both wash his
hands and to drink, but now he's saying look, there's not even
enough for you to drink and now you want to use what
the little that's left to wash your hands. אמר לו, amar lo,
he said to him: מה אעשה, mah e'eseh, what should I do?
שחייבין עליה מיתה, she-chayavin aleiha mitah, that if
one who transgresses rabbinic laws like washing the hands is חייב מיתה,
chayav mitah, like we said before, that it's how strict the rabbinic
laws are. Now again, by the way, the מהרש''א Maharsha says that
it's all connected to תרומה Terumah and eating תרומה Terumah when you're
טמא, tamei, which is חייב מיתה, chayav mitah, so he explains that
again we're not all rabbinic laws. Anyway, so what else should I
do? מוטב אמות מיתת עצמי ולא אעבור על דעת חבריי. mutav amut
mitat atzmi ve-lo e'evor al da'at chaverai. Better I should die my
own death, meaning that I'll die a natural
death and I won't go against the word of my colleagues and
be deserving of this heavenly death. It's quite fascinating because here the
idea of going against my colleagues on the one hand it could
sort of
lighten the sense of transgression that it's not like these greater and
previous generations made this edict it's my own
colleagues, and even so it's such a terrible transgression. And of course
it could also heighten the sense that in addition to the sense
of it being a law there's this sense of this obligation
and integrity that you have to this whole enterprise that you are
a part of and to your colleagues that are the ones that
actually were part of making this law.
Anyway, so he refused to do it. Of course one would say
that if you don't have enough water to wash if you either
have to choose between washing your hands and eating bread or drinking
you should drink which is a more greater necessity so even if
you're gonna make
that
He would refuse to eat anything until they brought him water to
wash his hands. So maybe that is what he did. He said
I'll use it to wash my hands but in the end maybe
he drank it and he didn't eat the bread and then because
they didn't want him to starve, this was maybe a first early
example of somebody going here on a hunger strike. So in order
that he shouldn't starve they brought him extra water to wash his
hands. כששמעו חכמים בדבר Kesheshamu chachamim badavar
when the sages heard about this they said, אמרו מה בזקנותו כך
Amru ma bizknuto kach if he had that type of a strength
in his old age to be willing to withstand that type of
a deprivation because, בילדותו על אחת כמה וכמה beyalduto al achat kama
vechama how much more so would he have had that inner strength
in his youth. ומה בבית האסורים כך Uma beveit haasurim kach if
he had that ability in the jail, שלא בבית האסורים על אחת
כמה וכמה shelo beveit haasurim al achat kama vechama again how much
strength he would have had to keep to the מצוות mitzvot when
he was not in the jail. Now of course this is not
actually the הלכה, halacha, take a look at תוספות, מוטב אמות מיתת
עצמי, mutav amut mitat atzmi, אף על גב דבפרק קמא אמרינן ארבעה
דברים פטורים במחנה af al gav d'veperek kama amrinan arbaah devarim pturim
bemachaneh ונטילת ידים, unetilat yadayim, right you learned that all over יום
טוב Yom Tov that you don't have to wash the hands if
you're in the camp, וכל שכן במקום סכנה, vechol shekein bimkom sakana,
מחמיר על עצמו היה machmir al atzmo haya he was מחמיר machmir
on himself which again sort of shows something here about the fact
that this is a little bit of rhetoric. It's not like you're
really חייב מיתה, chayav mita, it's not like he certainly wouldn't have
been, he wouldn't have even been transgressing, he would have been allowed.
So it just shows the heightened concern he gave to דברי חבריו
divrei chaveirav to the words of חכמים chachamim and to those who
were his actually his colleagues. Okay.
Now all of this is so we have a tremendous amount of
תורה שבעל פה, Torah sheba'al peh so much that we did on
ourselves, even the rabbinic laws, things that we added ourselves, how serious
they are. And this seems to all be leading up to where
we're going now and how this ties in to our theme, because
let's face it, עירוב Eruv. is pretty much all rabbinic law. So
let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda
Amar Shmuel, בשעה שתיקן שלמה עירובין ונטילת ידים beshaa shetikan Shlomo eiruvin
unetilat yadayim now
we are here attributing the תקנות takanot of עירובין Eiruvin and נטילת
ידים netilat yadayim for שלמה. Shlomo. נטילת ידים Netilat yadayim by the
way we just mentioned, right, and that was the whole story with
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and עירוב. So, יצתה בת קול ואמרה yatzta
bat kol veamra a heavenly voice came out and said, בני אם
חכם לבך ישמח לבי גם אני, beni im chacham libcha yismach libi
gam ani, my son if your heart is wise I will also
rejoice. So here in the enacting of rabbinic edicts, now attributed way
back to שלמה, Shlomo, these particular ones, God is rejoicing and again
gives a tremendous weight to these rabbinic edicts. ואומר חכם בני ושמח
לבי ואשיבה חורפי דבר. veomer chacham beni vesamach libi vaashiva chorfi davar.
So my son you've been wise and my heart is rejoicing and
I will return those who mock me a word. So right. So
דבר זה דרש
רבא davar zeh darash Rava
now who is saying this? So דבר זה דרש רבא, davar zeh
darash Rava, מאי דכתיב mai dichtiv, what's meant by the, just one
second let me just check רש״י Rashi here...
No. Okay.
So דבר זה דרש רבא, davar zeh darash Rava, מאי דכתיב what's
meant by the verse לכה דודי נצא השדה נלינה בכפרים נשכימה לכרמים
נראה אם פרחה הגפן פיתח הסמדר הנצו הרמונים שם אתן את דודי
לך. lecha dodi neitzei hasadeh nalina bakfarim nashkima lachramim nireh im parchah
hagefen pitach hasmadar henitzu harimonim sham eten et dodai lach. So nice
פסוק from שיר השירים. Shir HaShirim. Come my beloved let us go
out to the field and lie down in the villages, rise up
in the vineyards, we'll see if the vine has flowered, if
it's begun whether it's begun to blossom, the סמדר smadar is like
the unripe grape, whether the pomegranates have given forth flower, there I
will give my love to you. לכה דודי נצא השדה, Lecha dodi
neitzei hasadeh, come my beloved let's go out to the field, אמרה
כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amra knesset Yisrael lifnei Hakadosh Baruch
Hu, כנסת ישראל Knesset Yisrael said to God, ריבונו של עולם, Ribono
Shel Olam, master of the universe, אל תדינני כיושבי כרכים, al tedineni
kiyoshvei krachim, don't judge me like people that live in the city,
like those bourgeois people, שיש בהם גזל ועריות, sheyeish bahem gezel vaarayot,
that they have in them
stealing and sexual sin, ושבועת שוא ושבועת שקר ushvuat shav ushvuat sheker
and false oaths because they're so involved in business, it's all about
business and desire and lust and money. נצא השדה, Neitzei hasadeh, let's
come out to the
field, בוא ואראך תלמידי חכמים שעוסקים בתורה מתוך הדחק, bo vaarecha talmidei
chachamim sheoskim batorah mitoch hadechak, let me show you the תורה Torah
sages that they're not part of all of this disgusting business and
the city life, they live in a life of deprivation and all
they do is they learn תורה, Torah they're out in the field
they have nothing to them, none of this distractions, none of all
of this other stuff, they're just learning תורה. Torah, נלינה בכפרים, Nalina
bakfarim, we'll lie in the villages, אל תקרי בכפרים אלא בכופרים, al
tikri bakfarim ela bakofrim, the rebellers, that's an interesting shift, בוא ואראך
אותם שהשפעת להם טובה והם כפרו בך. bo vaarecha otam shehishpata lahem
tova veheim kafru becha. In contrast to presumably those in the city,
that you have given them so much goodness and you have given
them so much wealth and opportunity and look what they do, they
reject you, they deny
you. strong
condemnation of city life, which is
interesting. If, it's interesting that this is in, this is רבא, אמר
Rava amar, רבא Rava, דכתיב and this is a point that Dr.
Yaakov Elman makes
that, actually he makes that about
רב, רב in מחוזא. Mechuza. But anyway, that רב was, couldn't get
along with the people of מחוזא Mechuza and they were very much,
you know, city people and cosmopolitan and so on, but this is
רבא, Rava, so it doesn't actually work. But anyway, it is interesting
because very often the rabbis did live more in the cities than
in the villages, at least a lot of them, and this is
a strong condemnation of that city life. So maybe it doesn't mean
that they're not living in the city, but they're separating themselves away
from what they see as the evils of the city life. Okay,
נשכימה לכרמים, Nashkima lachramim, let us rise up to the vineyards. אלו
בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות. Eilu batei knesiot u'vatei midrashot. These are the
houses of, you know, prayer houses and houses of study. You remember
how the כרם ביבנה, Kerem b'Yavne, the rows of the study house
are like the rows of a vineyard. נראה אם פרחה הגפן, Nireh
im porchah hagefen, let's see if the vine has flowered. אלו בעלי
מקרא. Eilu ba'alei mikra. So these are the people of Torah of
who know the written Torah because it's, פיתח הסמדר, Pitach hasmadar, and
that's the unripe grapes. אלו בעלי משנה, Eilu ba'alei mishna, it's more
and more developed as you go from תורה שבכתב Torah shebichtav to
תורה שבעל פה. Torah sheba'al peh Right, and then the תורה שבעל
פה Torah sheba'al peh. and the תלמוד Talmud is what's held up
as the highest. הנצו הרמונים, Henetzu harimonim,
the actual pomegranates, which are much bigger than grapes, have flowered. אלו
בעלי גמרא. Eilu ba'alei gemara. שם אתן את דודי לך, Sham etein
et dodai lach, there I'll give my love to you. אראך כבודי
וגודלי, Arecha kvodi u'godli,
I would show you my honor and my greatness. שבח בני ובנותי,
Shevach banai u'vnotai, the praise of my sons and daughters, how amazing
it is all of the Torah that they have learned and the
תורה שבעל פה Torah sheba'al peh, that they have developed. Okay, so
an interesting thing about abandoning sort of city life for the simple
life of the בית מדרש. Beis Medrash. אמר רב המנונא מאי דכתיב,
Amar Rav Hamnuna mai dichtiv, what's meant by the verse, וידבר שלשת
אלפי משל ויהי שירו חמשה ואלף? Vayidaber shloshet alfei mashal vayehi shiro
chamisha va'alef? So
שלמה Shlomo
spoke three thousand משלים meshalim and his song was a thousand
and five. מלמד שאמר שלמה על כל דבר ודבר של תורה שלשת
אלפי משל, Melamed she'amar Shlomo al kol davar v'davar shel Torah shloshet
alfei mashal, on everything of the Torah, שלמה Shlomo three thousand, you
know, parables. ועל כל דבר ודבר של סופרים חמשה ואלף טעמים, V'al
kol davar v'davar shel sofrim chamisha va'alef teamim, and anything of the
sages he gave a thousand and five explanations. So
even the sages, again, emphasizing how much we have to give weight
to the rabbinic edicts, even those things of the sages have thousands
of deep explanations that we don't understand. So דרש רבא, Darash Rava,
now רבא Rava explicated, מאי דכתיב,
what's meant by the verse, ויותר שהיה קהלת חכם עוד למד דעת
את העם, V'yoter shehaya Kohelet hacham od limad da'at et ha'am, more
than Kohelet was wise he taught knowledge to the people, ואיזן וחיקר
תיקן משלים הרבה, V'izen v'chiker tiken meshalim harbeh,
he gave ears, whatever, or he gave to listen and he investigated
and he established many parables. אמר עולא אמר רבי אליעזר, בתחילה הייתה
תורה דומה לכפיפה שאין לה אזניים, Amar Ulla amar Rabbi Eliezer batchila
hayta Torah doma l'kfifa she'ein lah oznayim,
originally the Torah was like a pot that didn't have handles, או
לקופה, o l'kupa, baskets, I'm saying. עד שבא שלמה ועשה לה אזניים.
Ad sheba Shlomo v'asah lah oznayim. He made ears, he made handles
to the baskets. So basically and this is, no, I'm sorry, I
skipped a line. למד דעת את העם, Limad da'at et ha'am,
I'm sorry, דאגמרה בסימני טעמים. D'agmarah b'simanei teamim. I'm going back four
lines from the bottom. That he taught them like the סימני טעמים
simanei teamim which
basically means like טראפ, trop, he gave them טראפ, trop, you know,
way to break up the פסוקים psukim in the Torah or to
break up רש"י says even in the משנה. Mishna. ואסברה במאי דדמי
לה, V'asp'ra b'mai d'dami lah, and he also explained it by comparison.
So he established basic parameters of תורה שבעל פה. Torah sheba'al peh.
If you look at רש"י he says, דאגמרה בסימני טעמים קבע לה
מסורת וסימנים בין בתיבות המקרא בין בגרסא של משנה. D'agmarah b'simanei teamim
kava lah mesoret v'simanim bein b'teivot hamikra bein b'girsa shel Mishna. So
again, ascribing early stages of תורה שבעל פה, Torah sheba'al peh. not
only עירובין Eiruvin
and נטילת ידיים, netilat yadayim,
not only specific תקנות, takanot, but also the idea that there were
these traditions and these oral teachings and the same way we have
a whole מסורה mesora by the תורה שבכתב, Torah shebichtav,
שלמה Shlomo established the similar מסורה mesora by the תורה שבעל פה.
Torah sheba'al peh, And now we have the other דרשה, drasha, אמר
עולא אמר רבי אליעזר Amar Ulla amar Rabbi Eliezer, בתחילה הייתה תורה
דומה לכפיפה שאין לה אזניים, Batchila hayta Torah doma l'kfifa she'ein lah
oznayim, originally it was like a pot or a basket without ears,
עד שבא שלמה ועשה לה אזניים, ad sheba Shlomo v'asah lah oznayim,
until שלמה Shlomo made ears to it. Now what are the ears?
It could be tying into what we said before, you know, he
sort of type of a טראפ, trop, especially if it's an oral
culture, you know, there would be like a sing-song way in which
they would learn it, so that there was a type of a
טראפ trop and so on to the Torah, certainly תורה שבעל פה.
Torah sheba'al peh But רש"י says that it also actually goes back
to the earlier דרשה drasha of עירובין Eruvin and חומים, Chumim, excuse
me, of עירובין וידיים, Eiruvin v'yadayim, which means like a protector. כדפרש
רש״י k'defareish Rashi ועשה לו אזנים ve'asa lo oznaim תיקן עירובין וידיים
tikein Eruvin v'yadayim וגזר על שניות לעריות vegazar al shniyot l'arayot כמפורש
ביבמות k'mefarash b'Yevamot ביבמות b'Yevamot they also had him ascribe to him
the גזירה gezeira on transgressing, you know, rabbinic incest. ועל ידי כך
v'al yedei kach אוחזים ישראל במצוות ochzim Yisrael bemitzvot שיתרחקו מן העבירה.
sheyitrachaku min ha'aveira.
So therefore they're able to hold onto the מצווה. mitzvah. It's an
interesting different image than the fence. The fence is sort of protecting
against transgression, but here it's actually about, you know, here, although it
is somewhat related to transgression, it's interesting and I want to get
back to this point that עירובין Eruvin, and ידיים yadayim are more
like rabbinic מצוות mitzvot. than they are like rabbinic prohibitions. I mean
עירובין, Eruvin you know, עירובי
תחומין
Eiruvei
T'chumim and עירובי חצרות Eiruvei Chatzeirot is something that you're doing it.
עירובי תבשילין, Eiruvei Tavshilin, you know, something you make a ברכה bracha
on, and so on. There's a ritual at least somewhat to them
and it's more like a rabbinic מצווה. mitzvah. So rather than the
fence, it makes the idea of the handle. It gives you something
to support, to hold onto the מצוות. mitzvot. רש״י Rashi throws in
the עריות arayot because again, as long as you're not transgressing, that
also allows you to connect and support. You could have understood the
ears and the handle like I said about the טעמים teamim just
to own the knowledge of the תורה שבכתב Torah shebichtav and תורה
Torah. שבעל פה, but here it's kind of very much into the
עירובין Eruvin and the נטילת ידיים. Netilat Yadayim. Okay, so now we'll
do a little bit more. אמר מר Amar Mar and then I
want to get back to this point about עירובין Eruvin and נטילת
ידיים. Netilat Yadayim. אמר מר Amar Mar ומלמד שיש—I'm umelameid sheyeish sorry,
I skipped the line—קווצותיו תלתלים kvutzotav taltalim
like his locks, you know, are like—whatever, his hair's in locks. אמר
רב
חסדא אמר מר עוקבא מלמד שיש לדרוש על כל קוץ וקוץ תילי
תילים של הלכות. Amar Rav Chisda Amar Mar Ukva melameid sheyeish lidrosh
al kol kotz vekotz tilei tilim shel halachot. On every little tiny
little letter of the תורה שבכתב Torah shebichtav certainly, but given the
direction of the גמרא Gemara here, might even be on the rabbinic
law, but certainly on the תורה שבכתב, Torah shebichtav, you can make
piles and piles of הלכות halachot and again the size of the
תורה שבעל פה relative to the תורה שבכתב. Torah shebichtav. Before we
get to the next point, which is an interesting one, the next
אגדתא aggadata here, a pretty harsh one also I should say,
I wanted to say something about this issue about עירובין Eruvin and
נטילת ידיים. Netilat Yadayim. You know we make ברכות brachot on those,
and you make ברכות brachot on rabbinic מצוות. And it is interesting
to note that there are a couple of rabbinic מצוות we make
ברכות brachot on: חנוכה, Chanukah,
מגילה, Megillah
and in a number of these places the גמרא Gemara asks like,
you know, by חנוכה Chanukah it says, "What do you mean אשר
קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו? asher kidshanu bemitzvotav vitzivanu? היכן ציוונו?" heichan tzivanu? By
מגילה Megillah to some degree the גמרא Gemara, doesn't ask that because
מגילה Megillah is basing itself on פסוקים psukim and once מגילה was
part of the canon, which is another whole discussion how מגילה got
to be part of the canon, then you don't have to ask
anymore like היכן ציוונו. heichan tzivanu. But this whole idea about not
only rabbis making גזירות, gezeirot, עשו משמרת למשמרתי, asu mishmeret lemishmarti, but
making מצוות that then translate into אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו asher kidshanu
bemitzvotav vitzivanu creates, you know, new sets of types of questions of
what this means in terms of the whole rabbinic enterprise. You know
the בה״ג Behag for example counts some of these things, עירובין Eiruvin
and תחומין T'chumim, and so on—I have to check which ones, but
חנוכה Chanukah I believe, מקרא מגילה, mikra Megillah, some or all of
these he counts as part of his תרי״ג מצוות, Taryag mitzvot, which
doesn't necessarily mean that he thinks that they were given straight from
God, but it does mean the way in which he is, you
know, maybe understands when the גמרא Gemara says תרי״ג מצוות נאמרו למשה
מסיני Taryag mitzvot ne'emru l'Moshe miSinai it was a little imprecise; it
meant including rabbinic. But whatever he says it means, it still is
saying that these are part, you know, sort of become part of
actual מצוות. So it's interesting therefore that the גמרא Gemara of all
the things it could have established to שלמה, Shlomo, it's true in
another place it talks about שניות לעריות, shniyot l'arayot, but here picks
תחומין, you know, and
עירובין Eruvin and נטילת ידיים. Netilat Yadayim. I mean why those about
any other things and of the rabbinic sort of tradition that we
ascribe to him? And it seems that those are things that again
are of the small group of things that are not just rabbinic
prohibitions but actually rabbinic מצוות. So if we ascribe it way back
to שלמה Shlomo and we have פסוקים psukim now in קהלת Kohelet
that come to reinforce it, that sort of helps in terms of
these being sort of part of this whole thing of a rabbinic
מצווה. mitzvah. So I think that that's particularly what's going on here
and why those two are mentioned. I heard a nice explanation on
this פסוק once from Rabbi Mark Dratch who he said that the
עירובין Eruvin and נטילת ידיים Netilat Yadayim are because it's like a
good message to a rabbi. He says you have to decide, sometimes
there are things that require עירובין that you've got to get involved
in, and then there are other types of things, נטילת ידיים, Netilat
Yadayim, that you know that you have to step back and remove
your hands from and that you don't, you know, that discretion is
the better part of valor. Okay, let's take a look at the
beginning of the next אגדתא aggadata which raises some important challenging
issues.
So, שחורות כעורב, shachorot ka'oreiv, black as a raven, במי אתה מוצאן,
bemee ata motzan, and who do you find all of this תורה
that we've been talking about, במי—top bemee of כ״א עמוד ב׳—שמשכים ומעריב
עליהם לבית המדרש, the person who rises up and goes late tonight
in the בית המדרש. beit hamidrash. So that is שחורות shachorot like
שחר shachar and... like ערב Erev at night. So if you don't
think that it comes easy, you have to put in the hours.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, במי, Bemi, now רבא Rava says, במי שמשחיר
פניו עליהם כעורב, Bemi shemashchir panav aleihem ka'orev, somebody who blackens his
face on them like a raven, that you totally deprive yourself, going
back to the earlier גמרא Gemara about deprivation. You never go outside,
you never see the light and so on. רבא Rava אמר, now
רבא Rava says, במי שמשים עצמו אכזרי על בניו
ועל בני ביתו כעורב, Bemi shemeisim atzmo achzori al banav ve'al benei
beito ka'orev,
that you have to be willing to become cruel to your wife
and your children like a raven. You abandon them and you just
completely devote yourself for תורה and you don't respond to their needs.
כי הא דרב אדא בר מתנא, Ki had deRav Ada bar Matna,
like רב אדא בר מתנא, Rav Ada bar Matna, הוי קאזיל לבי
רב, Hadei ka'azil levei Rav, he went to the house of רב,
אמרה ליה דביתהו, Amra lei devatayu,
so his wife said to him, ינוקי דידך מאי עביד להו, Yanukei
didach mai avid lehuh, what about
your children, what am I going to do with them? I mean,
you know, you're not earning a living. אמר לה, Amar lah, he
said to her, מי שלימו קורמי באגמא, Mi shelimu kurmei be'agma, what,
are there no longer any reeds in the swamp? So go ahead
and cut down those reeds and chew on those reeds or something
like that. So very, a very unfeeling, it's very interesting given the
whole speech recently by what's-her-name, by
Ruth Calderon in the כנסת because sometimes the גמרא, Gemara she was
referring to the גמרא Gemara in כתובות Ketubot that was very critical
of
this whole approach, and that's true, the גמרא Gemara in כתובות Ketubot
is very critical of this approach and here there's a גמרא Gemara
that actually is praising it. So the question about what is the
גמרא's attitude to this type of abandoning of wife and children for
the sake of תורה, most of the time it is very negative
but there are some גמרות Gemarot that are positive about this. And
I should say that the וילנא גאון Vilna Gaon has a commentary
on משלי Mishlei and in his commentary on משלי, Mishlei, he actually
quotes this גמרא and goes at great length talking about
how important it was
to, this idea of completely abandoning עולם הזה Olam Hazeh and abandoning
the needs of your wife and children etc. just for the sake
of learning תורה. So it is a גמרא that does play an
influence among those who would otherwise
among those who want to actually prove of this type of a
lifestyle. I do want to go back by the way, I was
just checking, I don't know why I made this mistake, I was
right the first time, you know what they say, last time I
thought I was in error, I made a mistake, that it is
רבא Rava, in מחוזא Mechuza and it actually very much fits so
this whole critique of the city life, and I do think that
this is a point that this גמרא that Dr. Elman uses a
lot in his expanding on the whole idea of רבא, Rava we
often find that it's רבא Rava who is very much fighting the
people of מחוזא Mechuza and they hate him and he tries to
give them מוסר, Mussar, so it actually is רבא Rava who's the
one who gave this very strong critique of city life, which fits
in with what we know about רבא and מחוזא. Mechuza. Okay, good
night, I will see all of you tomorrow.